<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature and danger of heresies, opened in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons, Ianuary 27. 1646. at Margarets Westminster, being the day of their solemn monthly fast. / By Obadiah Sedgvvick, B.D. Minister of Gods Word at Covent-Garden.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E372_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201317</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 59:E372[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature and danger of heresies, opened in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons, Ianuary 27. 1646. at Margarets Westminster, being the day of their solemn monthly fast. / By Obadiah Sedgvvick, B.D. Minister of Gods Word at Covent-Garden.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.F. for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Brazen serpent in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelations XII, 15-16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Heresies, Christian --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113986:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE NATVRE and DANGER OF HERESIES, Opened in a Sermon BEFORE THE HONOURABLE Houſe of COMMONS,</hi> Ianuary 27. 1646. <hi>at</hi> Margarets Weſtminſter, <hi>being the day of their ſolemn Monthly Faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By OBADIAH SEDGVVICK,</hi> B. D. <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Gods Word at</hi> Covent-Garden.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>PET.</hi> 2. 1.</bibl>
               <p>But there were falſe Prophets alſo among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Yee therefore beloved, ſeeing yee know theſe things before, beware leſt yee alſo being led away with the errour of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſſe: but grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <bibl>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17, 18.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed by</hi> M. F. <hi>for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND, at the Brazen ſerpent in</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:113986:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Mercurii</hi> 27. <hi>Januar.</hi> 1646.</head>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, that Sir <hi>Peter Went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> doe from this Houſe give thanks unto Mr <hi>Sedgewick</hi> for the great pains he took in his Sermon preached on this day at <hi>Margarets Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> before the Houſe of Commons, and that he doe deſire him to Print his Sermon. Wherein he is to have the like priviledge in printing of it, as others in the like kind uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſing. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I Appoint <hi>Samuel Gellibrand</hi> to Print this Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>OBADIAH SEDGEVVICK.</signed>
                  <date>Febr. 19. 1646.</date>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113986:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE The Houſe of COMMONS now aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving received your commands to preach, that which firſt preſented it ſelfe unto my thoughts, was the ſubject of this enſuing Diſcourſe; A Theam (if I doe underſtand the preſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of theſe times) both ſeaſonable and neceſſary. There are ſome points of difference which are of an inferior con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and ſtand farther off from the foundation; theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but <hi>Judicia domeſtica,</hi> I meddle not with: But there are other poſitions which pull hard at the very foundation, and which doe ſubvert the faith, <hi>dogmata ſalutis devora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſtyles them; and <hi>Religionis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae Carcinomata,</hi> as another ſpeaks: againſt theſe I held it my duty, as a Chriſtian, as a Miniſter of Chriſt, and as your ſervant to declare my ſelf; And I beſeech you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom was it more fit to open thoſe ulcerous ſores, then before your ſelves <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> who under God are our moſt choice and tender Phyſitians?</p>
            <p>If any Reader ſhould now be ſo unhappy in his charity as to calumniate this diſcovery of hereſies and blaſphemies to be an arrow ſubtilly deſigned againſt holineſſe and good men: to ſuch a one, all that I would reply is this; 1. The ſureſt friends to holineſſe have been the ſharpeſt enemies to errours; Chriſt and his Apoſtles were ſo. 2. That I never
<pb facs="tcp:113986:3"/>
yet have learned what direct advantage did at any time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to true ſanctity, by a patient endurance of hereſie and blaſphemy. 3. Nor can I be ſo uncharitable as to think, that any perſon ſincerely holy, or incending the progreſſe of holineſſe, durſt be a friend to ſuch damnable and ſoule-deſtroying errours. The deſign which I would commend to all in this time of Reformation, is this, That <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> (which are ſo naturally combined, and ſo mutually intereſted) <hi>may be conſcientiouſly promoted with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall zeal:</hi> encourage holineſſe, but contend for the truth too: maintain the truth, but countenance holineſſe too: he who pretends holineſſe, but regards not truth; and hee who pretends the truth, but regards not holineſſe, neither of theſe is a cordiall friend either to truth or holineſſe. For your parts <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> be you pleaſed to goe on (as you have begun) in the ſtrenuous ſupport of them both: Both of them have a neceſſary reſpect to Gods glory: both of them have a neceſſary reſpect to mans ſalvation: both of them have a neceſſary reſpect to our preſent Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: both of them will prove the Kingdomes ſafety, your conſciences comfort, and the crown of all your long and great labours. For both theſe you have the prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt unworthy, yet moſt faithfull Servant, OBADIAH SEDGVVICK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113986:3"/>
            <head>THE NATURE and DANGER OF HERESIES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>REVEL. 12. 15, 16.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And the Serpent caſt out of his mouth water as a Floud after the woman, that he might cauſe her to bee carried away of the Floud.</p>
                  <p>And the earth helped the woman, and the earth opened her mouth, and ſwallowed up the Floud which the Dragon caſt out of his mouth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text is a ſeaſonable Text; Seaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the times wherein we live, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to the worke of this day, which ſhould be humbling work, and reforming work; The parts of the text are two: 1 <hi>A new Danger, v.</hi> 15. 2 <hi>A renued Succour, v.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The <hi>New Danger</hi> is ſet forth in four particulars. <note place="margin">The Diviſion of the Text.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Author</hi> of it <hi>[And the Serpent]</hi> There is a former danger mentioned in <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13. And that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113986:4"/>
was managed by the wrathfull Dragon: And here is a New danger, which is contrived by the cunning Serpent: Open cruelty is more dreadful, but ſubtill policy is more pernicious: The cunning Devill is a more miſchievous enemy to the Church of Chriſt, then the raging Devil: <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> were ſore enemies to the Church, but of all, the Emperour <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> is reputed the worſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>Engine</hi> of it, <hi>[The Serpent caſt out of his mouth]</hi> It is a queſtion amongſt the School-men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>peccataoris</hi> may not be worſe then <hi>peccataoperis?</hi> Sure I am, that the danger which comes out of the mouth of the Serpent, far exceeds that danger which depends upon the ſword of the Dragon.</p>
            <p>There is a mouth of truth, and that is Gods mouth: there is a mouth of peace, and that is Chriſts mouth: there is a mouth of prayer, and that is the good mans mouth: there is a mouth of curſing, and that is the wicked mans mouth: there is a mouth of miſchiefe, and that is the Serpents mouth. When the Devil wracked <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> then he uſed the mouth of the Serpent: And when he deceived <hi>Ahab,</hi> then he became a lying ſpirit in the mouth of the falſe Prophets: And when he would deceive the whole world, then he fals into the mouth of the Beaſt to ſpeak great things: And here intending to deſtroy the Church, hee uſeth the mouth of the Serpent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the <hi>Matter</hi> of it: <hi>[And the Serpent caſt out of his mouth water as a floud]</hi> It is not ſaid, that he did caſt out water onely, (and yet even that dropping out of the mouth of a Serpent had been ſufficiently dangerous) but he did caſt out water as a floud: Flouds in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture are the periphraſes of extreameſt dangers; when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113986:4"/>
the danger is ſudden, high, violent, quick, it is then expreſſed by the metaphor of a floud: <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>flouds of ungodly men, Pſal.</hi> 18. 4. And the Prophet ſpeaks of the <hi>enemies comming in like a floud, Eſa.</hi> 59. 19.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the <hi>ſcope or intention</hi> of it, <hi>[That he might cauſe the woman to be carried away of the floud]</hi> There was a floud which did bear up the Ark, but here is a floud to overwhelm and drown the Ark: which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Devil and his Angels attempt againſt the Church of Chriſt, not leſſe then the utter ruine of it is ſtill the aim and project: when the Devil rageth as a Dragon, then his intent is utterly to waſt; and when he acts as a Serpent, then his deſign is utterly to ſink the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Thus you ſee the Churches <hi>New Danger:</hi> but now behold the Churches <hi>Renued Succour:</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is very remarkable, that this Chapter is as full of ſuccours, as it is of dangers; In <hi>v.</hi> 7. you may read of the <hi>Dragon and his Angels appearing in the field and fighting,</hi> but then you read of <hi>Michael and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſuccouring even to victory, v.</hi> 8, 9. Again, in <hi>v.</hi> 13. you find the Dragon <hi>perſecuting the woman which brought forth a man-child;</hi> but then alſo you read, that there was given to the woman <hi>two great wings of a great Eagle, that ſhe might flie into the wilderneſſe, v.</hi> 14. And here you ſee a floud caſt out to carry away the woman, but withall you read of a gracious and preſent ſuccour; <hi>[And the earth helped the woman by opening her mouth, and ſwallowing up the floud which the Dragon caſt out of his mouth.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have the diſtribution of the Text. Now I proceed to the Propoſitions which may be obſerved from it. The whole ſtate and ſumme of this Text may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113986:5"/>
be reſolved into theſe three Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the miſchief which Satan cannot compaſſe by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the Text.</note> 
               <hi>open cruelty, he will aſſay againſt the Church of Chriſt by ſubtill policy: when he fails as a Dragon, then he will try what he can doe as a Serpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Serpents floud is the chiefeſt and the worſt of the Churches dangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Lord hath ſtill raiſed freſh ſuccours for the Church, againſt the freſh dangers of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt of theſe, I intended to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated both the truth of it, and the practiſe of it in all ages of the Church, as alſo the ſeverall methods, wiles, ſtratagems, and deſigns of Satan upon, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of Chriſt: and the reaſons of ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his hand, and making uſe of his mouth, of deſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from open cruelty, and of falling to his wiles of policy: And then alſo the wonderfull miſchief which hath redounded thereby, that whereas his cruelty hath killed thouſands, his policy hath ſlaine ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands: where alſo might have been diſcovered, 1. The advantages of policy above cruelty. 2. The generall receptivity or capacity in men to be catched by the policies of this Serpent. 3. The uſuall inadvertencies rather under the workings of the Serpent, then of the Dragon. 4. The ſpecious wayes of inſinuating his miſchief in the ways of policy: But I was taken off from my purpoſe in the handling of this point (though as to my own opinion, very neceſſary and excellent) becauſe I ſhould thereby check my ſelf in the handling of the ſecond point, which I deſired chiefly to diſcourſe upon this day before this Honourable Auditory: And therfore omitting other things, I addreſſe my ſelf unto that Propoſition which ſhall be the onely ſubject of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113986:5"/>
my preſent pains: The Propoſition is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Serpents floud, is the chiefeſt and the worſt of</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>the Churches dangers: [The Serpent caſt out of his mouth a floud to carry away the woman.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Interpreters are carried away with ſeverall conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures concerning this floud which is caſt out to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away the Church: There is a floud of tears, and a floud of reproaches and ſlanders: That is a floud wherein we ſhould drown our ſinnes; this is a floud wherein men drown our names: And there is a floud of perſecution, and a floud of invaſion, and a floud of <note place="margin">Severall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this floud.</note> erroneous opinions: which of theſe three latter it is, may be queſtioned. Some, by this floud of waters, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the floud of bloud let out by the Pagan <note n="*" place="margin">Praeſertim Maxentii &amp; Maximini edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta, reſcripta, mandata tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis inſculpta, &amp; paſſim ſuffixa de Chriſtianis toto orbe tollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, extirpandis.</note> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: A red ſea was that floud; they endeavoured all they could to drown the Church in its own bloud: But this opinion is not very probable, becauſe the former danger in the practiſes of the Dragon compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended this floud, and it ſeems clearly to be mentioned already in <hi>v.</hi> 11. where it is ſaid, <hi>They loved not their lives unto the death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others by this floud, underſtand the irruption of the <hi>Franks</hi> and <hi>Vandals, Hunnes</hi> and <hi>Longobards,</hi> who about the year 400. brake in upon <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> like a tempeſt, and a ſwelling inundation, and in a ſort overwhelmed the Chriſtian world: This I confeſſe was a floud, but whether that which is implied in the Text, I much doubt, becauſe the Text ſpeaks of a <hi>floud caſt out of the mouth of the Serpent:</hi> But in the irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe fore-mentioned people, there was neither the Serpent, nor the mouth: It was a plain, publike, notorious cruelty, managed by the hand, not a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger managed by ſecret ſubtilty, and in the mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113986:6"/>
               <hi>Viegas</hi> by this floud underſtands a ſtrange kinde of Antichriſt, who ſhall ſend out his Army into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and by his <hi>Satellites</hi> (ſurely he means ſome Purſivants or buſie Emiſſaries) ſhould ſearch caves and dens to find out the faithfull, whom the earth (in a literall ſenſe) ſhould ſwallow up as it did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiram:</hi> but this fancy is not worth the confuting, onely this let me ſubjoyn, that ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters doe faſten this floud upon the <hi>true Antichriſt of Rome,</hi> and queſtionleſſe virtually it will reach him as to the practiſe; but whether it will reach the Text as to its principall ſcope, I queſtion.</p>
            <p>But not to trouble you with more conjectures, the beſt Interpreters which I have met with, unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">David Chytrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Bullingerus. Pareus, &amp;c.</note> expound this particular floud of waters, to be thoſe <hi>notorious errors, hereſies, blaſphemies, (dogmatum porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta)</hi> and <hi>ſchiſmes,</hi> which Satan by ſeverall inſtruments did caſt out to the infection of the Church, and to the ſubverſion of the faith, immediately under the Chriſtian Emperours: when the Church of Chriſt obtained a little reſpite from the cruell ſword, and began to enjoy ſome breathing tranquillity, then on a ſudden, there brake out, 1. That floud of the <hi>Arian hereſie</hi> (even in the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Deity of the Son of God was oppugned and blaſphemed. And this floud roſe ſo high, and ran ſo ſwift, that in a ſhort time it overwhelmed the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and after that the <hi>Weſt,</hi> ſo that (in a manner) the whole world turned <hi>Arian.</hi> 2. And after that another floud brake out, the <hi>Macedonian</hi> hereſie, oppoſing the Deity of the holy Ghoſt: ſoon after this the <hi>Pelagian</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, againſt the whole Goſpel: And the <hi>Neſtorian</hi> and <hi>Eutychian</hi> hereſie, againſt the verity of the perſon of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113986:6"/>
Chriſt, which flouds continued upon the Church for near 300. years; and what miſchiefs did accrew unto the Church of Chriſt by every one of them, you may abundantly read in <hi>Euſebius, Socrates, Euagrius, Sozomen, Theodoret,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>So that now we are come (in ſome good meaſure) to perceive what this floud caſt out of the mouth of the Serpent is: namely, <hi>erroneous, falſe, wicked, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall doctrines, caſt out of the mouths of corrupt and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting ſeducers; oppoſing the truth, and endangering the very</hi> eſſe, <hi>or beeing of the Church of Chriſt:</hi> Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, favour me with your patience, whiles I ſhew unto you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the nature of hereſies and erroneous doctrines which the Serpent doth caſt out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the danger of them to the Church of Chriſt: that they are perillous and hazardous.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the greatneſſe of that danger, it is the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and worſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſome pertinent uſefull applications of all this to our ſelves for our preſent humbling and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. <hi>Of the Nature of hereſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To find this out, you may be pleaſed to know, that the word <hi>hereſie,</hi> admits of a threefold ſignification and uſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sometimes it is taken for any <hi>new and ſelect opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> contrary <hi>to the common and uſually received opinions of other men:</hi> in which reſpect the word <hi>(hereſie)</hi> may ſometimes bear a good conſtruction, <hi>For after that way</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 24. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>which the Iews called</hi> hereſie, <hi>did</hi> Paul <hi>worſhip the God of his Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Sometimes for <hi>any falſe opinion whatſoever, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113986:7"/>
                  <hi>a perſon recedes from any divine truth, and thereby fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments diviſions, ſects, contentions:</hi> in which reſpect, <hi>dihaereticon</hi> with <hi>Iſidore,</hi> is all one with <hi>diviſivum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But ſtrictly amongſt Divines, it is taken <hi>for ſome notorious, falſe, and perverſe opinion, oppoſing and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> as <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaks, or overthrowing the forme of wholeſome words, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks: and it may be thus deſcribed:</p>
               <p>Hereſie <hi>is an erroneous or falſe opinion, repugnant unto</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hereſie what.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſubverting of the doctrine of faith revealed in the Word, as neceſſary unto ſalvation: And obſtinately main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and pertinaciouſly adhered unto by a profeſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Hereſie is an <hi>erroneous opinion, falſaſententia,</hi> or <hi>falſum dogma;</hi> there is a difference 'twixt <hi>malum opus</hi> and <hi>hareſim:</hi> an evill work is one thing, hereſie is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing: In the work which a man doth, there may be ſin, very much ſin, but properly there is not hereſie: <hi>Erratum</hi> it may be, but <hi>error</hi> it is not, unleſſe it reſides in the underſtanding: The works of hypocriſie, and of prophaneneſſe (as murder, injuſtice, adultery, theft, &amp;c.) have much wickedneſſe in them, but unleſſe theſe become the objects of opinion as well as of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, they are not hereſies. Indeed, if beſide the morall practiſe of them, any one riſeth to an intellectuall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that the practiſe of them is lawfull, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Word of God; now ſuch an opinion, erroneous opinion of them may come to an hereſie: yea, let me add a little more, though many practicall works be acted <hi>conſcientia repugnante</hi> (as <hi>Alfonſus à Caſtro</hi> in this caſe ſpeaks) yet the works (ſimply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as works) are not to be reputed hereſies; For then every ſin againſt knowledge ſhould be hereſie:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113986:7"/>
no, it is not light ſhining and working againſt an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or work, which raiſeth it to be an hereſie, but it muſt be light in the Word ſhining againſt an opinion, which muſt denominate it to be hereſie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hereſie is an erroneous opinion <hi>concerning matters of faith.</hi> There are <hi>quaeſtiones</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiones</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as one well diſtinguiſheth: every erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. Nazianz. Oral.</hi> 14.</note> opinion is not hereſie: If the error be of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>praeter fidem,</hi> it is not hereſie, let the error be what it will; to make the erroneous opinion amount to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, two things muſt concurre.</p>
               <p>One, that the errour be <hi>circa fidem:</hi> although a man doth erre in his own opinion within the proportion of <hi>objectum ſcibile,</hi> as againſt the rules and principles of ſeverall Sciences, (as Geometry, Aſtronomy, Naturall Philoſophy) yet this errour is not hereſie: For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is an erroneous opinion, not <hi>circa ſcibile,</hi> but <hi>circa credibile;</hi> not about matters of humane Science, but about matters of divine faith; But if the errour be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the matters of faith revealed in the Word, as that Chriſt is not God, or is not Man, here now the errour will riſe to hereſie, for here is <hi>dogma fidei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another is, that the errour be <hi>contra fidem:</hi> againſt the faith, as well as about the faith: If it be an opinion contrary to ſound doctrine, overthrowing the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this will make the errour to be hereſie: An opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion may be contrary, not onely to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many particular Traditions, but alſo to the judgement of ſome godly men, yet is it not therefore an hereſie: but then is it hereſie when the opinion is <hi>contra fidem Traditam,</hi> contrary to the faith, to the doctrine of faith in the Scriptures. Nevertheleſſe here we muſt carefully conſider, that an opinion may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113986:8"/>
be ſaid to be contrary to the Faith in a double reſpect, 1. One is, when it is not concordant to every truth whatſoever, which is revealed in the Scriptures. I dare not ſay, that every error in this reſpect is hereſie, there may be many miſtakes, many <hi>incauti errores,</hi> (as one ſpeaks) perhaps diſſonant to the true Chronology, to the exact and full hiſtory of ſome places, yet theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently are not hereſies. 2. The other is, when it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to that truth, or any truth which is neceſſary to ſalvation, and here queſtionleſſe, the errour <hi>contra fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi> will prove to be hereſie: Hereſie is <hi>opinio perverſa &amp; adverſa:</hi> there may be opinions diverſe, yet none of them bee hereſies: In the Interpretation of the Scriptures there is frequently a variety of opinions, but as long as like the lines of a circumference they doe meet in the Center, as long as every one of them unites and harbours within the analogy of faith, here is no hereſie, though ſome variety: But then it is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, when the opinion is adverſe, is contrary to, is ſubverſive of the faith revealed as neceſſary unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: which the opinion may be, either</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Explicitely:</hi> As when the errour is manifeſtly fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall, it doth expreſly pluck up the foundation: It is not a problematicall canvaſing of a truth, but a plain Gunpowder-plot, an error which blows up a fundamentall truth: It doth not blow off the tiles of the houſe, but blows up the bottomes and ſupports of the houſe; As when a perſon denies the Godhead of Chriſt, redemption by Chriſt, ſalvation by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Or <hi>Reductively:</hi> As when the errour overthrows that which being denied and overthrown, the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereupon, and thereby, is by an inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity alſo denyed and overthrown; or maintains that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113986:8"/>
which being maintained, a fundamentall truth muſt neceſſarily and unavoidably be ſubverted: As if any perſon ſhould maintain, humane ſatisfactions to be ſufficient to merit and procure ſalvation: this error would neceſſarily ſubvert mans ſalvation founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the merits of Jeſus Chriſt onely.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the erroneous opinion be againſt <hi>any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular doctrinall neceſſary truth,</hi> even that particular errour will amount to hereſie: Indeed number (if I may ſo ſpeak) is requiſite to apoſtaſie, but any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar neceſſity of a truth to our ſalvation (if oppoſed) is ſufficient for hereſie: The Apoſtate turns his back from the whole truth, the Heretique grapples vvith ſome truth, but denies other truth: And therefore though a perſon ſtill retaines an aſſent conſonant to many truths, nay to moſt truths, nay to all except one neceſſary truth, yet if his erroneous opinion be ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of that one, his errour will come to hereſie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To make the erroneous opinion to be hereticall, it is neceſſary (as to the perſon who holds it) that he be <hi>a profeſſed Chriſtian,</hi> one who is <hi>vinculo fidei obſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> as ſome doe word it: It is a queſtion put by Schoolmen and others, whether Infidels, Pagans, and Jews, who hold opinions contrary unto, and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the faith, are to be reputed Heretiques? Unto which it is anſwered, that one may be ſtyled hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, either, 1. Materially, as when his opinion for the matter and ſubſtance of it, is contrary to the faith, and ſubverting of the foundation; 2. Or elſe formally, as when not only the ſubſtance of the opinion is hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and oppoſite to the Chriſtian faith, but alſo it is maintained by one who hath formerly engaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the profeſſion and maintenance of the faith; In
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113986:9"/>
the former conſideration, Infidels and Jews may bee reputed Heretiques; but in this latter conſideration, onely he is ſo to be reputed, who was reckoned amongſt the number of Chriſtians profeſſing the faith: If the Infidel and Jew deny Jeſus Chriſt to be a Saviour of ſinners, though this be a great ſin, yet it is not (ſtrictly conſidered) an hereſie, becauſe neither the one nor the other ever embraced or profeſſed the Goſpel: But if a Chriſtian profeſſing the Goſpel doth this, in him it is hereſie.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But laſtly, to make up hereſie, there muſt be <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy or pertinacy</hi> joyned with that erroneous opinion which is contrary to the faith: He who is an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique muſt adhere or inhere, he muſt obſtinately ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here or cleave unto his erroneous opinion: I confeſſe that it is a very quick caſe, Whether pertinacy be ſo eſſentiall to hereſie, that the opinion cannot at all be reputed hereticall, unleſſe the profeſſing Chriſtian (who holds it) appear obſtinate? Concerning which caſe I will onely deliver my opinion (ſubmitting it to better judgements) that where the erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion doth <hi>ex natura opinionis,</hi> appear groſly and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly exitious to the raſing of the foundation, it is hereticall; A denying of Jeſus Chriſt to bee the Son of God, or a denying of ſalvation by him, ſuch an opinion in the very nature of it is pernicious, rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and damnable: yet <hi>ad plurimum,</hi> and in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way of diſcovery and proceſſe with Heretiques, I humbly conceive, that pertinacy muſt be an ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to conſtitute the perſon to be heretically errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: And therefore in this point of Hereſie and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, Divines doe diſtinguiſh <hi>inter Infidelem,</hi> and <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium in fide,</hi> and <hi>Haeretico credentem, &amp; Haereticum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113986:9"/>
There is <hi>Infidelis,</hi> one who never entertained or profeſſed the faith, yet is obſtinately and moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently carried againſt it. This man may be a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but he is not an Heretique, notwithſtanding his opinion, and notwithſtanding his obſtinacy.</p>
               <p>Again, there is <hi>dubius in fide,</hi> one who is doubtfull in the faith: one who is wavering and reeling <hi>(anceps &amp; fluctuans)</hi> his anchor doth not faſten, he is not quite on, nor quite off, but ſtaggers and totters: the equall apprehenſions of truth and falſhood doe ſo poiſe and ballance the one againſt the other, that he comes not up fully and determinately any way: Now although ſome doe affirm, that even <hi>dubius in fide</hi> is <hi>Haereticus,</hi> yet I dare not to aſſert it; <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle did <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitare in fide,</hi> he was <hi>Incredulus,</hi> yet ſurely not <hi>Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus;</hi> Indeed as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaks, he who doth <hi>dubitare</hi> doth <hi>errare:</hi> for the man doth erre who approves falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood for truth, or diſallows truth for falſhood, or takes uncertain things for certain truths, or certain truths for uncertain conjectures: errour here is, but not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
               <p>There is alſo <hi>Haeretico-credens:</hi> one who is rowled up, wrigled in, packt up into a dangerous errour: miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſeduced, follows his leader: holds that which really is contrary to the faith, and deſtructive: yet not out of obſtinacy of minde, but upon an imagination of truth: not out of deliberation, but by ſurreption; he is utterly deceived by taking upon truſt: his erroneous opinion is not fortified with pertinacy, but only crept into him by his ſimplicity; And therefore being can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly dealt with, and being admoniſhed, he contends not, but yeelds, and wheels about to the truth: as the bow when the ſtring is taken off returns to its own po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113986:10"/>
again, ſo upon admonition the ſeduced perſon quits his errour, and ſubmits to the faith.</p>
               <p>But then there is <hi>Haereticus,</hi> the very Heretique; and he is one who doth not only <hi>(malè ſentire)</hi> erre in his opinion, but alſo doth <hi>(fortiter tenere)</hi> obſtinately maintain that errour: he doth not onely hold <hi>(fidei oppoſitum)</hi> that which is contrary to the faith: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he doth hold the ſame <hi>(animo opponendi)</hi> with a pertinacious ſpirit: There is in him <hi>definiendi temeritas, &amp; tuendi perverſitas</hi> too; But here now fals in that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and knotty queſtion; namely, when a perſon is to be reputed obſtinate or pertinacious in holding an errour contrary to the faith: The Apoſtle, I think, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves us in this, where he ſaith, <hi>An Heretique after the firſt and ſecond admonition, reject.</hi> So then, when <note place="margin">Titus 3. 10.</note> there is a due propoſall of the truth manifeſtly revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Scriptures, and yet the erroneous perſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres unto his errour our of a very pravity of mind, and will not ſuffer his underſtanding to be captivated unto the truth, this perſon is pertinacious in holding of his erroneous opinion, and is manifeſtly an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</p>
               <p>Beloved! when an erroneous perſon maintains his opinion contrary to clear light, ſo that he muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily deny the truth of God or revoke his error: or when he cannot maintain his wicked errour, but he muſt neceſſarily overthrow ſome other article of faith, which yet he would not doe: or when the perſon cares not to trample down another truth to uphold his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror againſt a former truth, makes one article a foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool to pull down another; or when the perſon ſteps from one errour to a more groſſe one, cares not what errour he plungeth himſelf into, ſo that he may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113986:10"/>
his errour: or when all ſolid reaſon is ſilenced; nay, if reaſon and conſcience might ſpeak, they doe (concurring with the truth againſt his errour) ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemn him, and having nothing to reply, hee fals unto proud ſcorns, bitter virulencies, miſerable ſhifts; ſurely ſuch an erroneous perſon is obſtinate and pertinacious in his corrupt opinion.</p>
               <p>And thus briefly for the firſt queſtion, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Nature of Hereſies. I now come to handle the ſecond particular, which reſpects the Danger of Hereſies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Of the Danger of Hereſies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That hereſies, or erroneous doctrines and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are dangerous, cannot be ſo much as a ſcruple to any Chriſtian upon the earth, unleſſe he be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Heretique or into an Atheiſt. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Scriptures doe <hi>in terminis</hi> charge ſin, and perniciouſneſſe, and damnation upon them. S. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons up hereſies amongſt thoſe <hi>workes of the fleſh</hi> which ſhut perſons out from inheriting the Kingdom of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 20, 21. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> cals them <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and damnable,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>bring ſwift deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and ſpeaking of the Authors of them, he ſaith, that <hi>their damnation ſlumbers not,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3. A mans o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion makes him ſinfull, as well as his practiſe; and a man may be damned for a corrupt opinion, as well as for a corrupt converſation. I will not put it to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whether a ſin againſt the rule of faith may not <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> be far more ſinfull and damnable then the ſin which is againſt the rule of life? But let it (for the preſent) ſuffice, that if hereſies and heterodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies be ſuch ſins, be ſuch locks as can ſhut up the gates of heaven againſt a ſoul: If they be ſuch bars as can
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113986:11"/>
break up the doors of hell, and bring damnation: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that man is not himſelf, who doubts whether they be dangerous or no.</p>
               <p>Secondly, let us conſider unto what dangerous things, hereſies and corrupt doctrines are compared in Scripture, and by what dangerous creatures hereticks and falſe teachers are expreſſed, by them you may judge whether hereſies are dangerous yea or no.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For hereſies, they are compared in Scriptures ſometimes to a <hi>Gangrene</hi> or canker, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Their word will eat as doth a canker:</hi> The canker is an inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ulcer, creeping from joynt to joynt, corrupting one part after another, till at length it eats out the very heart and life. Sometimes to a <hi>ſhipwrack,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 19, 20. <hi>Hold faith and a good conſcience, which ſome having put away concerning faith have made ſhipwrack:</hi> In what a condition are the miſerable paſſengers, when their ſhip is ſplit aſunder by the Rock? All their goods are loſt, and all their lives too. <hi>Chriſt</hi> cals them <hi>leaven, Paul</hi> cals them a <hi>bewitching:</hi> Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writers call them a <hi>leproſie, poiſon, fire,</hi> a <hi>tempeſt,</hi> our text, a <hi>floud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And as for Heretiques, they are expreſſed by creatures very dangerous and hurtfull; ſometimes they are ſtyled <hi>foxes, Cant.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>The foxes which ſpoil the grapes;</hi> ſometimes they are called <hi>dogs,</hi> rending <hi>dogs, Phil.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Beware of dogs, beware of the conciſion;</hi> ſometimes they are ſtyled <hi>wolves, grievous wolves which devour the flocks, Acts</hi> 20. 29. Sometimes they are in effect called very <hi>mountebanks,</hi> and <hi>cheaters, ſuch as beguile unſtable ſouls, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles doe give ſpeciall charges and caveats againſt them, to take
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113986:11"/>
heed and beware of them, which they never vvould have done, had they not been dangerous, <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 15. <hi>Beware of the leaven of the Phariſees,</hi> Matth. 7. 15. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe Prophets, Matth.</hi> 24. 4, 5. <hi>Take heed that no man deceive you, for many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many,</hi> Phil. 3. 2. <hi>Beware of dogs, beware of evill workers, beware of the conciſion,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 17. <hi>Beware leſt ye alſo being led away with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſſe:</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly all theſe things doe clearly prove that there is a danger in them.</p>
               <p>But that is not all: danger is not all, there is yet more then meer danger in them, which will appear in the reſolving of the third particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3. <hi>The greatneſſe of danger by Hereſies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hereſies are the greateſt and higheſt of dangers to the Church of Chriſt: you will imagine that the ſword, and priſon, and exile, and diſperſion, and ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and torments, and tortures, and the moſt cruell deaths which befell the Church in the Primitive times, were extreamly dangerous, and ſo they were; but yet not half ſo dangerous as the flouds of hereſies and corrupt opinions are. The Church ever gained by the former, grew more in purity, in unity, in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in zeal and courage: But did it ever get ſo by he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and erroneous doctrines? Unleſſe by accident, and after much ſtriving, and phyſicking for recovery.</p>
               <p>I will goe no farther then the Text it ſelf, to ſet out unto you the exceeding miſchief &amp; danger which comes by hereſies and erroneous doctrines. They are in the Text ſtyled a floud caſt out of the mouth of the Serpent: Now ſeriouſly conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are a <hi>corrupting and defiling</hi> floud; Any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113986:12"/>
floud is ſo, it preſently defiles the pure waters, ſpoils the grounds, leaves filth and ſlime and mud behind it: But ſurely a floud that comes out of the mouth of a poiſonous Serpent is ſo: And there are 4 precious things, which wicked errors or hereſies doe poiſon, corrupt, and defile.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, the <hi>ſouls of men:</hi> And is there a more noble and choice thing in man, or belonging to man then his ſoul? Our ſoul is of more value then all the world: But hereſies and wicked doctrines corrupt the ſoul, nay many ſouls: It was the heavy Indictment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> that <hi>in her were found ſlaves and ſouls of men, Rev.</hi> 18. 13. Heretiques in one place are called <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, (making merchandiſe of you with fained words,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 3.) In merchandizing there is ſomething bought for a certain price: In this merchandiſe, the ſouls of people are bought for fained words, for baſe metall, onely for a corrupt errour: Every hereticall opinion buyes a ſoul, or ſtabs a ſoul. It ſtabs the ſoul of him that maintains it, and ſtill it trades on to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der more ſouls: It lifts off the ſoul from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon which the ſalvation of ſouls is built. What will become of an houſe whoſe foundation is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? And what will become of a ſoul whoſe bottome for ſalvation is denyed and rejected? Damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies make us to <hi>deny the Lord that bought us,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. Oh what is this! what will follow upon this, when a poor ſinner comes to deny the Lord Ieſus who bought him!</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, <hi>the leading faculty of the ſoul:</hi> There is more danger to corrupt a Captain, then to corrupt many private Soldiers, and moſt danger to corrupt a Generall, who leads the whole Army: It is capitall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113986:12"/>
in ſome places, and at ſome times, to caſt poiſon into the ſpring; this will poiſon all the ſtreams: Hereſies corrupt the great leader of the whole ſoul: The Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man is the Generall, the Admirall, the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, the Overſeer, the Guide, the Eye, the <hi>Primum movens</hi> for the reſt of the ſpheres in man; If the light in man be darkneſſe, how great is that darkneſſe? If the Iudgment be infected, how dangerous is that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? Beloved! If there be the darkneſſe of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from inapprehenſion in the minde, the ſoul here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is in an ill caſe; If there be the darkneſſe of miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion by errour, it is in a worſe caſe; But when that miſguiding errour befals the leading faculty of all the ſoul, and this errour fals point-blank againſt a truth neceſſary unto the mans ſalvation: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over this errour is ſtifly adhered unto by that leading judgement: it doth miſlead, and it will miſlead: Oh now in what a deſperate condition is the whole ſoule hereby? If it doth not recover of this error, it dies for it, and it can never be recovered, til the judgment be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; And when will that judgement be altered, which perverſly affronts and rejects the light of truth, which onely can carry it off?</p>
               <p>The third is, the <hi>moſt active faculty of the ſoul;</hi> they doe defile and corrupt the conſcience: Now this is amazedly dangerous. A wicked errrour is blinding, whiles in the judgement onely: but it is binding when it ſlips to the conſcience alſo. It is a wrangling Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in that, but it is a working Ieſuite in this; Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes falling amongſt the vitall ſpirits, are moſt quick, and moſt dangerous; Errours are never more perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, then when they drop into the conſcience: for whatſoever engageth conſcience, the ſame engageth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113986:13"/>
all, and the utmoſt of our all: If the conſcience of man be made a party againſt the truth, now all that a man hath, and all that a man can doe, will be made out againſt the truth too: Now the perſon will with <hi>Paul</hi> grow mad, and deſperate againſt <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing engaged by an erroneous conſcience, conſents to the death of <hi>Stephen,</hi> yea could he (in that condition) have met with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf, he would have done the like againſt him.</p>
               <p>The fourth is, <hi>The converſations of men:</hi> Hereſie is ſeldom or never divided from Impiety; <hi>Hymeneus,</hi> who <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 19.</note> made ſhipwrack of faith, made ſhipwrack alſo of a good conſcience: Thoſe whom <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>dogs,</hi> he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cals <hi>evill workers.</hi> And in another place, ſpeaking of <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 2. Tit. 1. 15, 16.</note> ſome <hi>whoſe mindes were defiled,</hi> he adds, <hi>and reprobate to every good work.</hi> Our Saviour ſpeaking of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſaith, <hi>you may know them by their fruits:</hi> The lives of men are conſonant to the judgements of men: Truth and goodneſſe are reciprocal, and ſo are falſhood and wickedneſſe: The doctrine of faith is a doctrine of holineſſe too: And the doctrine of lies, is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of prophaneneſſe too: He who fals from truth to falſhood, will quickly fall from piety to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Truth is of a reforming vertue, as well as of an informing nature: It ſalts and ſeaſons heart and life both: but that errour which putrifies the heart, will putrifie the life alſo: the plague will at length riſe and break out into bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es and botches.</p>
               <p>They who write the ſtory of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> begin <note place="margin">Sleid. &amp;c.</note> it with errour in their judgements, but end it vvith wickedneſſe in their practiſes: And <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing long ſince of <hi>Novatus,</hi> (that peſtilent Heretique) ſaith <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 49. <hi>ad Cornelium.</hi>
                  </note> thus of him: That he was <hi>(rerum novarum cupidus)</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113986:13"/>
one who itched after new notions; <hi>(avaritiae inexplebili rapacitate furibundus)</hi> and beyond meaſure covetous, <hi>(arrogantia &amp; ſtupore ſuperbi tumoris inflatus)</hi> intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably proud; <hi>(curioſus ſemper ut prodat)</hi> no man ſo pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no man ſo treacherous; <hi>(ad hoc adulator ut fallat)</hi> he would commend you before your face, but cut your throat behind your back; <hi>(nunquam fidelis ut diligat)</hi> as falſe a perſon as lived; <hi>(Fax &amp; ignis ad conflanda ſeditionis incendia, turbo &amp; tempeſtas ad fidei facienda naufragia, hoſtis quietis, tranquillitatis adverſarius, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis inimicus)</hi> a very fire-brand, cared not what became of truth or peace, turned the world upſide down, ſo that he might carry on his opinion.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaking of Antichriſt (who is the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſignanus</hi> of all Heretiques) cals him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that man of ſin; no ſuch ſinner as he: <hi>Lyranus</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, one totally given up to ſin; and <hi>Theophylact,</hi> the ringleader of ſin: And truly, it is moſt juſt with God to give them up to corrupt lives, who rejecting his truth, have given up themſelves to corrupt errors and lies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hereſies are <hi>a drowning and overwhelming floud:</hi> a floud (you know) is ſuch a collection, ſuch an heightning confluence of waters, as ſwels the rivers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their bounds, and lays all under water. Now there are three things which hereſies doe overwhelm. <note place="margin">See 2 Pet. 2. 2.</note> One is, <hi>the glory of all glories:</hi> the glorious Name of God, the glorious Name of Chriſt, the glorious Name of the holy Spirit, the glorious name of divine truths, Hereſie turns the glory into a lye: It gives God the lye, and Chriſt the lye, and the holy Ghoſt the lye; For it gives truth the lye, the Scriptures the lye, which are the glory of God, and Chriſt and the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113986:14"/>
He who makes the Word of God a lyer, makes God himſelf a lyer; O ſirs! what is God without truth? and what is all the goodneſſe of the Goſpel without truth? and what is all the fabrick of mans ſalvation without truth? Truth is as it were the pin, the claſp, the knot that ties all; pull out that, untie and break that, the excellencies of God, the glories of Chriſt, the ſweetneſſe of promiſes, the ſouls of men, the ſalvation of mens ſouls, all are daſhed, are broken, are gone: And ſuch work doth hereſie make, it doth diſſolve the bond of all glory; yea, it doth reſolve God into worſe then nothing: No God is better then a falſe god, there is an open or ſecret blaſphemy in all hereſies: No man can contemn the truth of God, but in that he muſt likewiſe condemn the God of truth.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, <hi>the glory of Religion:</hi> Religion is clipt and darkned: It grows low and beggerly, when it is patched with errour: It is a debaſing of the gold to marry it with any metall of a courſer birth; All Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is by ſo much the more excellent, by how much the more of truth it hath; but when once it is adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated, when once it is tainted and leavened with dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable errours, now the ſilver is become droſſe, the glory is departed from it: when a Religion is like the feet of <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> image, which were part of clay, and part of iron, now it becomes low and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible: If the mixture of humane inventions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates of its glory, what an impairing is the mixture of corrupt, and poiſonous, &amp; faith-ſubverting doctrines?</p>
               <p>The third is, not onely the dignity, but alſo <hi>the very vitall entity of a Church:</hi> Truth is the ſoul of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and falſhood is death unto it: Schiſmes do it much hurt, but nothing like vile doctrines: Schiſmes doe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113986:14"/>
only rent the coat, but Heterodoxies do rent the heart: thoſe pluck up the fence, but theſe pull down the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: thoſe doe tear away the childrens lace, but theſe doe bereave the children of their bread: thoſe are a turbulent ſea, theſe are a dead ſea: thoſe doe ſcratch, but theſe doe kill: Men talk much of un-churching, and of Antichriſt, and limbes of Antichriſt, but a Church is never more near to give up the ghoſt, then when it is moſt near to give up the truth: It is never nearer to be un-churched, and to be eſſentially An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſted, then when the truth fails, and when abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable hereſies and corrupt doctrines ſwarm in it: Mark ſeriouſly that place in 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 3. <hi>Every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God,</hi> and this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt: I, this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt. The ſpirit of errour and falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hereſies are <hi>a ſuddenly riſing floud:</hi> A floud is no ſober or quieſcent puddle, no grave or ſlow-paced river; but it is a quick and extemporary collection and inundation: And truly herein lies the greatneſſe of the danger unto a people and Church by hereſies, that they are quickly conceived, and quickly brought forth: quickly born, and quickly thriving: though truth gets on very ſlowly, by reaſon of that incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the judgement for ſupernaturals, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that naturall oppoſition in man to the things of God, and by reaſon of the ſubtill interpoſition of the Prince of darkneſſe, who blinds the minds of men, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel ſhould ſhine unto them, yet erroneous and falſe opinions do break out with eaſe and ſpread ſwiftly: they are like the plague which is a flying arrow: there needs no
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113986:15"/>
preparation of the ground for nettles; if the ſeeds doe but drop down, you may ſoon have a full crop: yet the ground muſt be prepared again and again to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good ſeed: the hearts of men are naturally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſuck in errours, as they are to ſend out wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes: the tinder is ſo prepared to catch the fire, that it is but the ſtriking of the flint, and the work is done; The Scriptures doe compare falſe doctrines to leaven, O how faſt doth a little leaven ſowre the lump? <hi>Paul</hi> wondred that the <hi>Galatians</hi> were ſo ſoon removed to another Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 6. The good man ſlept but one night, and the field was ſowen all over with tares by the wicked and envious man: How quickly did the world turn <hi>Arian?</hi> How ſuddenly did the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> endanger <hi>Germany?</hi> The Vines which have been ſome months in growing, are in very few howres torn down and deſtroyed by Foxes and wilde Boars. Now if erroneous doctrines be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo highly pernicious, and in their operation ſo ſpeedily diffuſive, then certainly they are of all other things the moſt dangerous to the Church of Chriſt: A plague which ſuddenly infects many families, is therefore the more dangerous: and hereſies vvhich can ſuddenly infect many ſouls, are therefore the more dangerous evils.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hereſies are an <hi>increaſing and ſwelling floud:</hi> A floud at firſt makes the river onely to look big, and to run a little thicker and faſter: but after a while it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the river to be unruly, to break in pieces, to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabound, the waters contribute on every ſide, and at every corner, to raiſe and mount it, ſo that there is no paſſing: Falſe doctrines at firſt ſeem to be modeſt, they will be but ſcruples and quaere's, and then they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113986:15"/>
come to be probabilities; and then they come to be <note place="margin">Like the ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Leproſie.</note> tolerable concluſions; and then they riſe to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable tenets: and then fit to be made publique articles: and then neceſſary to be held; and then the contrary not to be maintained or ſpoken for, nay to be diſdained and reproached.</p>
               <p>But this is not all neither: For as falſe opinions riſe thus and encreaſe in their direct line of particular magnitudes, by way of intention: ſo doe they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enlarge themſelves in divers breadths by way of extenſion: They are like circles in a pond, one circle begets another, ſo doth one hereſie beget another, a leſſer begets a greater. As one morall ſin is but a ſtaire to ſtep down lower, ſo this intellectuall ſinne of hereſie, it is but a ſtaire to help up to higher and worſe errors.</p>
               <p>If you will conſult Hiſtoricall Antiquity, it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull to behold the great flames bred out of ſmall ſparks: what monſtrous opinions have been built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on errours which ſeemed but little at the firſt: how one errour hath hatched a greater: they who write of them can diſtinctly tell us where the man was firſt planet-ſtruck, (what his firſt errour was) but after a while they are non-pluſſed in the account, the number of errours have doubled &amp; trebled; ſuch a maze and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth is errour; It is like a whirle-pool which firſt <note place="margin">Dato uno ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdo, mille ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur.</note> ſucks in one part, and then another, and never defiſts untill it draws in and plungeth the whole body. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ancient examples, wee may ſee this ſwelling growth of erroneous opinions in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where one errour ſtill advanced to more errours, and thoſe again to higher errours, and theſe ſtill running on, until a general corruption enſued from all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113986:16"/>
compare the firſt defections and corruptions with their laſt and preſent, how little then, how totall now, how particular then, how univerſall now, and you will eaſily acknowledge what encreaſing flouds erroneous opinions are; The points at firſt were rather about private intereſts of precedency, but they have been ſo encreaſed unto all doctrinals, that they are ſcarce ſound in any: Their errours about the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and Traditions, and the offices of Chriſt, and humane ſatisfactions and merits; and invocation and adoration of Saints; and of juſtification and faith, and good works, and free-will, and Sacraments, &amp;c. are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all the world: I could give unto you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance alſo in the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> whoſe firſt Author there (ſaith <hi>David Chytraeus</hi> in his Dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Epiſtle to <hi>Ericus</hi> King of the <hi>Swedes)</hi> was <hi>Nicolaus Pelargus Cygneus</hi> about the year 1523. his erroneous doctrines though bad enough, (for they were laid in the contempt of the Miniſtery of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and rejection of the Civill Magiſtrate, and <hi>in nova ac coeleſti luce immediate accenſain corde</hi> (as my Author expreſly relates) yet were not formerly ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, but when theſe opinions deſcended unto <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Munzerus</hi> and <hi>Andreas Caroloſtadius,</hi> now they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſwell both in the quantity of the opinions, and in the vaſt number of diſciples too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi> in his Annotations and Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Book <hi>De haereſibus &amp; quod vult deum,</hi> addes to that account, the many derivations and enlarging propagations of hereſies from age to age: ſhewing exactly the ſeverall hereſies flowing from ſome one capitall and originall hereſie, as from <hi>Simon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">See his <hi>Arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Haereſcón,</hi> as himſelf ſtyles it.</note> 
                  <hi>Magus</hi>'s hereſie: and from that of <hi>Valentinus,</hi> and that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113986:16"/>
of <hi>Cardo,</hi> and that of <hi>Artemon,</hi> and that of <hi>Novatus,</hi> and that of <hi>Arius, &amp;c.</hi> In which elaborate work of his, you may read of ſuch a ſtrange growth of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, that they never left multiplying and breeding, untill they had (as much as in them lay) overthrown and caſhiered every perſon in the Trinity: All the Scriptures, Law and Goſpel; every diſtinct morall commandement, every particular article of faith, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, Preaching of the Word, Baptiſme, Lords Supper, &amp;c. There are 4. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall heads unto which (uſually) we reduce Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion: 1. To the Decalogue of the Law. 2. To the ſymbole of faith. 3. To the Lords Prayer. 4. To the Sacraments. And that learned <note n="*" place="margin">See him <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſc. indice tertio. p.</hi> 142. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> printed at Geneva M. D. LXXXIII. in folio.</note> Author doth by name inſtance the ſeverall hereticall and erreonous teachers who have invaded every one of theſe, and in every particular comprehended in them: By all which, it doth moſt clearly appear how dangerouſly miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous hereticall opinions are to the Church of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There is one thing more which I would add in the laſt place, by which it ſhall be manifeſted, that theſe hereticall opinions are more dangerous then any other flouds, and that is <hi>a diverſe quality in them:</hi> other flouds are quickly up, and quickly down: although they grow high and perillous, yet there is a ſuddain tranſiency in the height and perill: their principles are unconſtant though violent, and being ſpent, theſe ordinary flouds ſink and famiſh for want of ſupply and feeding. But the flouds of falſe and erroneous doctrines are ſuch, as quickly riſe, but do very ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abate: They are in this reſpect worſe then the great deluge in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> which continued many months, but then did ſlack and ſink, and fell quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113986:17"/>
It is not ſo with hereticall errours, but they are like diſeaſes which come upon us flying, but goe away from us creeping: ſome erroneous opinions have been kept up for forty years together; nay above 100. years together: ſome of them 300. years: nay, ſome of the Antichriſtian heterodoxies have been kept up above a 1000. years together. O Brethren! men doe extreamly dote upon their own fancies, they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly pleaſed with their own brats, eſpecially with the new conceptions of their own minds, they dearly like them, and love them, and foſter them: For one Heretique who hath been poyſoned in his judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials, you may finde a thouſand of others converted and reduced who have onely been ſtained in their morals: Hereſie, or the hereticall opinion is ſtilted up by all the parts, arguments, ſhifts, learning of carnall reaſon; and it is born up by an haughty, and diſdainfull, and proud ſpirit; and it is ſo fallacious and fraudulent when you come to handle it, &amp; (which is not the leaſt) it is ſo rammed in with obſtinacy and peremptorineſſe, that it is almoſt a miracle to work effectually upon an Heretique.</p>
               <p>Every Heretique is odiouſly proud: All other men who diſſent from him, are far below him; and one ſaith very truly, <hi>That no proud man can endure to bee accounted a fool or a knave:</hi> So ſimple as to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, or ſo baſe as to deceive: one of which the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique thinks he muſt take to his ſhare, if at any time he recants his hereticall and ſeducing doctrine.</p>
               <p>I ſhould now come to ſhew unto you the reaſons why Satan makes uſe of this dangerous floud againſt the Church, and why eſpecially at ſome times more then other: He well knows that there remains in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113986:17"/>
Chriſtians many advantages for him as to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous opinions, much ignorance, much pride, and ſelf-conceitedneſſe, much itching vanity, much vain glory, much fraternall envy, much careleſneſſe and inadvertency, &amp;c. but I muſt wave this, and conclude all with ſome ſeaſonable applications unto our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Are hereſies, erroneous and falſe doctrines ſuch a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> and pernicious floud to the Church of God? Is there ſo much ſinfulneſſe in them? ſo much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Chriſt? ſo much injury to the truth of God? ſo much hazard to the immortall ſouls of men? O then, what juſt, what ſad, what ſingular cauſe have all of us (this day) to enlarge our tears and humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? There are many flouds which doe call for our tears: 1. The floud of innocent bloud in <hi>Ireland.</hi> 2. The floud of cries from poore widows and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans. 3. The floud of needy and wounded ſoldiers; and there is yet another floud, a worſe floud, the floud of hereſies and blaſphemies: one deep cals for another, the floud of wicked and ungodly opinions doth call earneſtly for a floud of ſorrow and lamentation.</p>
               <p>We are (by Gods mercy and goodneſſe) indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſcued from the cruelty of <hi>Dragons;</hi> O but now we are as much endangered with the floud of the <hi>Serpent:</hi> the bodies of people are (in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) ſecured from the edge of the ſword: but what of this, whiles the ſouls of people are hazarded with the poyſon of errours? If the danger flies from the body to the ſoul: if the corporall danger be exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a ſpirituall danger, where is our happineſſe, what is our ſafety by this?</p>
               <p>Beloved! there are 4. notable reaſons of our moſt <note place="margin">Note.</note> ſolemn humiliation for the ſpirituall wickedneſſes, for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113986:18"/>
the falſe and abominable doctrines, which (like a floud) are now overflowing this Nation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The account or height of ſome of them:</hi> They a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to no leſſe then execrable blaſphemies: to ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious, contemptuous, diſgracefull reproaches of God, and Chriſt, and the holy Scriptures: Beleeve me, blaſphemy is a daring ſin: It preſſeth very cloſe and too ſore upon God: <hi>He that blaſphemeth the Name of the Lord, he ſhall ſurely be put to death,</hi> Lev. 24 16. The words according to the originall are, <hi>Hee that ſtrikes through the Name of Jehovah:</hi> Blaſphemy is that bold ſword which is hacking of God himſelf, which is as it were cleaving of him aſunder: The School-men tell us, that blaſphemy breaks out 3. ways.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Cùm attribuitur Deo, quod ei non convenit,</hi> when we affirm that of God, which is unbeſeeming of God, which is incompatible with his holy and divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: As to make him a creature, or a lyer, or cruell, unjuſt, unmercifull, ſinfull, or the cauſe of ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Cum à Deo removetur, quod ei convenit:</hi> when we deny that to God, which indeed belongs to God: It is called blaſphemy in the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> when he ſaid, that <hi>the Lord was not able to deliver Hieruſalem out of his hand,</hi> 2 Chron. 32. 17.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Cum attribuitur creaturae, quod Deo appropriatur:</hi> when we put that upon a creature, which is proper to God: Thus when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had made a molten Calf, and ſaid, <hi>This is thy God that brought thee up out of Aegypt;</hi> it is added, and they wrought great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, <hi>Nehem</hi> 9. 18. In the Hebrew it is, and <hi>they committed great blaſphemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now compare this ſhort diſcourſe of the kindes of blaſphemies, with the many expreſſions let fall in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113986:18"/>
ſpeeches of ſome, and ſet down in the writings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and then judge whether ſome of our moderne errours riſe not as high as blaſphemy. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That God is the Author of ſin:</hi> Not onely of the actions unto which ſinne doth cleave, but of the very ſinfulneſſe it ſelf: of the ataxy, pravity, irregularity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Saints in this life are fully perfect, as om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient as God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That the fulneſſe of the Godhead doth dwell bodily in every Saint, in the ſame meaſure as it did in Chriſt Ieſus, whiles he dwelt here on earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>That when the fulneſſe of the Godhead ſhall be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the Saints, then they ſhall have more power then Chriſt had, and doe greater works then he did, and that then they ſhall have divine honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And one hath been complained of, for ſaying, <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt was a Baſtard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Another, <hi>that himſelf was Ieſus Chriſt, the Meſsias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>That Ieſus Chriſt is not God eſſentially, but nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>That his humane nature was defiled with originall ſin as well as ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>That he is not of an holier nature then men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>That it is as poſsible for Ieſus Chriſt to ſinne, as it is for a childe of God to ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>That there is no ſuch thing as the Trinity of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>That the Scriptures are but of an humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a meer ſhadow, a falſe Hiſtory, and ought not to be the foundation of any mans faith, more then the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha, <hi>and other Books, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> heard the blaſphemies of <hi>Rabſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kah, he rent his clothes, and covered himſelf with ſack-cloth,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113986:19"/>
                  <hi>and went into the houſe of the Lord, and ſent to the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>ſaying, This is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of blaſphemy:</hi> That day of blaſphemy was a day of trouble and vexation to him: though the blaſphemy was from an <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> yet it was a day of trouble to him; and what ſhould the day be unto us, when it is a day of many blaſphemies, and that not from profeſſed <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> but from profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? what Chriſtian can hear, can bear ſuch indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and reproaches caſt upon his God, and his Chriſt, without a bleeding and riſing ſpirit?</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>The breadth or number of falſe and erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions:</hi> ſo many, ſo grievous, as <hi>quis fando temperet à lachrymis?</hi> verily they grow ſo thick, ſo abundant, that they will leave us neither Church, nor State, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſtery, nor Ordinances, neither duties, nor worſhip. There are ſome who have printed large Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogues of them, I will but pick a few of the more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious of them, and ſpread them before you this day, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scriptures of the Old Teſtament doe not binde us Chriſtians, nor thoſe of the New neither, any farther then the Spirit (for the preſent) reveals un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, that ſuch a place is the Word of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That God never loved one man more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the world, and that the Decrees are all conditionall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That there is no Originall ſin.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the will of man is ſtill free, even to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturals.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the Saints may fall totally and finally from grace.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That Chriſt died alike for all: yea, that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113986:19"/>
ſalvificall vertue of his death extends to all Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, as well as to the Elect: yea, to the very Devils as well as unto men.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That Jeſus Chriſt came into the world not for ſatisfaction, but for publication: Not to procure for us, and unto us the love of God, but onely to be a glorious publiſher of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That God is not diſpleaſed at all, if his children doe ſin; and it is no leſſe then blaſphemy for a child of God to ask pardon for his ſins.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That Sanctification is a dirty and dungy quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That the doctrine of Repentance is a ſoul-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying doctrine.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That faſtings and humblings are legall and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That the ſouls of men are not immortall, but mortall.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That there is no heaven, (to crown the godly) nor hell (to torment the ungodly.)</p>
               <p n="14">14. That Civill Magiſtracy is Antichriſtian; and but an uſurpation.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That the whole Miniſtery of the Land, as to their preſent Ordination and ſtanding, is Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That it is as lawfull to baptize cats and dogs, and horſes, (which ſome have done for ſome of them, if not for all and more) as it is to baptize the infants of beleevers.</p>
               <p n="17">17. That there is no true Miniſtery, &amp;c. this day in all the world; nor was ſince the generall Apoſtaſie, which (they ſay) began ſince the death of the laſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113986:20"/>
18. That there will be none neither untill ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles be raiſed up and ſent: and when thoſe Apoſtles come, then there will be true Evangeliſts alſo, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and not till then. Hearken O people, and judge O Chriſtians, whether the Serpent hath not caſt out his floud amongſt us! Judge whether the errours in our times doe not call for more high thoughts, and more deep tears!</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>The length or perill by all theſe:</hi> If the perill were confined onely to the ſouls of them who are the craftſmen and founders of theſe opinions, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this ſhould move us to lament; but the floud is running, the water is ſpreading: The plague is not onely begun, but waſting: the contagion grows to be generall: It is got into the City, into the Countrey, got into that (other) chief Univerſity: the poiſon is dropt into the ſpringo: It is got into many leaders of the people, who doe themſelves erre, and cauſe others to erre, It breaths, and walks, &amp; rowls up and down. It is ſpreading over the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: It ſurpriſeth place after place, infects family after family: The ſword of late was not ſo ſwift to conquer bodies, as errours now are to poiſon ſouls.</p>
               <p>Truly Sirs! If blaſphemies againſt God, if reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt Chriſt, if deciſions againſt the holy Ghoſt; If contempt of the Scriptures, if vilifying of the Ordinances of Chriſt, if obloquies to our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſion, If the eternall hazard of ſouls, if all theſe cannot affect us, afflict us, I know not what to ſay unto you.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>The ſpeciall engagements which are upon us all, to lay all theſe things with ſorrow to our hearts.</hi> Beloved! we are Chriſtians (let others think of us as they pleaſe)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113986:20"/>
we are covenanting Chriſtians, (let others deride this as they liſt) and we are, or ſhould be penitent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (let others be what they pleaſe) now.</p>
               <p>Conſider us <hi>as Chriſtians,</hi> we take our ſelves to be the children of the true and living God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelves to be the members of Ieſus Chriſt; The faith of Chriſt is delivered unto us: we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with it, we are reſponſable for it: we are to be zealous for it. How then can we ſuffer our God, our Chriſt, our faith, to be thus diſhonourably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured and abuſed, and not be troubled at all!</p>
               <p>Conſider us <hi>as covenanting Chriſtians:</hi> ſo we have every one of us bound our ſouls to God, (can any mortall creature here releaſe us?) we have lifted up our hands to the moſt high God (in our ſeverall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) to extirpate hereſies and falſe doctrines.</p>
               <p>Yea, conſider us <hi>as penitent Chriſtians:</hi> faſting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould be ſo, they ſhould be mourning Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: And Chriſtians who penitentially mourn, will mourn for the ſins of others, as well as for their own ſins. And they will mourn moſt, when God is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured moſt: and can God be more diſhonoured, then by blaſphemies and damnable hereſies? Put all theſe together, and then conſider whether theſe ſins of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and blaſphemies ſhould not wound our ſoules with grief, which have wounded our God with ſo much diſhonour?</p>
               <p>But I paſſe from this Uſe of Humiliation, unto a <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> ſecond Uſe, which ſhall be for <hi>Exhortation;</hi> and it is this; Since there is ſuch a floud caſt out of the mouth of the Serpent to carry away the woman, let us care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully improve the following words in the Text <hi>[And the earth helped the woman, and opened her mouth to</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113986:21"/>
                  <hi>ſwallow up the floud:]</hi> Before I diſtribute my Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, let me premiſe a diſtinction or two.</p>
               <p>There is a twofold opening of the mouth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this floud: One is <hi>to ſpeak for damnable errours</hi> and opinions and ſuch as vent and maintain them; O that the mouth of any Chriſtian ſhould ever open it ſelfe in the behalfe of thoſe who dare open their mouths in blaſphemy againſt their God and Chriſt! Should the welfare of a corrupt and poiſonous ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer be dearer to thee, then the glory of thy God, then the truth of thy Saviour? But there is another ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the mouth, and that is <hi>againſt damnable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and blaſphemies:</hi> we can doe nothing <hi>againſt the truth, but for the truth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul: Contend earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iude: Hold faſt the faithful Word, for there are many unruly and vain talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and deceivers, whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped, who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert whole houſes, &amp;c.</hi> So the Apoſtle in <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p>Again, there is a twofold ſwallowing up of this floud; one <hi>by way of impreſsion and furtherance, of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and countenance:</hi> as when the fiſh doth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the bait: too many ſwallow up the floud in this ſenſe: <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſly, and my people love to have it ſo,</hi> Jer. 5. 31. <hi>There ſhall be falſe teachers, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, and many ſhall follow their pernicious ways,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 1, 2.</p>
               <p>Another is <hi>by way of hinderance and repreſsion,</hi> ſo as to make the danger of this floud to ſink and ceaſe; O bring in your help, bring it in fully, bring it in ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily (thus) to ſwallow up the floud: Beleeve it, if you doe not carefully ſwallow up this floud, this floud will ere long ſwallow you up, and the Kingdome too.</p>
               <p>Now there are two ſorts of men eſpecially, who
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113986:21"/>
may help, and who ought to help to ſwallow up and ſuppreſſe the preſent floud of hereſies and blaſphemies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You (Right Honourable!) and the reſt who are Chriſtian Magiſtrates. It was but the ſcornfull ſpeech of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> that the gods alone muſt remedy the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries offered unto them: O no! you are <hi>cuſtodes utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque tabulae:</hi> you are deſigned to be Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: you have received the ſword to be a terrour to the evill. Pious and learned <hi>Ameſius,</hi> ſpeaking to that queſtion, Whether Heretiques are to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Civil Magiſtrate? Anſwers thus, <hi>Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus locus &amp; officiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſtulat ut reprimat improbos turbatores</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In caſ. conſc. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>q.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>gladio, vel poteſtate publica &amp; externa ſi opus fuerit:</hi> It is his place and duty to repreſſe them, and reſtrain them, if they be noxious and turbulent: yea, and hee addes more then every one will be patient to hear: namely, that if alſo they be manifeſtly blaſphemous and pertinacious, they may be cut off <hi>ſupplicio capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali:</hi> according to that in <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. 15, 16. But I will not fall upon the diſcuſſion of that at this time: all that I would humbly ſuggeſt unto you, is this, That you may help againſt this dangerous floud 9. ways.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By <hi>a peremptory abhorring, and cruſhing of that floud-begetting maxime,</hi> viz. <hi>a Catholique liberty and tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all opinions:</hi> There was a Religion (as one once ſpake before you) <hi>omnium Deorum,</hi> of all Gods amongſt the old Romans: and there is a Religion <hi>omnium San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> of all Saints now amongſt the Papiſts: and if the Serpent could but wriggle in a Religion <hi>omnium opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum,</hi> of all opinions amongſt the Engliſh, he needs to deſire no more: If men can ſtep from one Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all, they will ſoon fall from all Religion to none.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>a publique declaration againſt all hereſies and</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113986:22"/>
                  <hi>blaſphemies, known to be ſpoken and printed;</hi> When <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorodius</hi> and <hi>Vaidovius</hi> ſtarted out their <hi>Socinian</hi> Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodoxies in the Low-Countries, the <hi>States Generall</hi> packt away thoſe ſeducers with exile, and publickly condemned and committed their peſtiferous bookes to the fire.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>making ſome ſtanding Laws againſt ſuch opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> which can be proved to be hereticall and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous; <hi>Serviunt reges terrae Chriſto</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>etiam leges ferendo pro Chriſto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>ſetting up your Church-Diſcipline with full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> that ſo it may reach theſe hereſies and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which (if any ſins) then they doe plainly fall within the Verge of it: If the diſcipline were fully and generally eſtabliſhed, you ſhould not have an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie or blaſphemy, or any erroneous opinion creeping out in any part of the Kingdome, but there would be a timely diſcovery of it, and likewiſe a ſpirituall remedy to recovererring perſons, and to prevent their further ſpreading.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By <hi>encouraging and heartning the godly, orthodoxe painfull Miniſters of the Goſpel, in their aſſertings and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatings of the truths of Chriſt: and in their oppugning of wicked, dangerous and damnable opinions:</hi> Not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (therefore) to be ſnibbed, abuſed, reviled, ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſlandered, diſturbed, hazarded, becauſe they doe oppoſe the adverſaries of truth, and thoſe Serpents which doe caſt out flouds amongſt us: why ſhould the Shepherd be diſcouraged, becauſe he keeps off Wolves from the ſheep? or any man bee checked, becauſe he would quench the flying fire?</p>
               <p n="6">6. By <hi>uſing your prudent Authority, in a timely cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be ſent forth faithfull and able Miniſters,</hi> ſuch
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113986:22"/>
as are throughly tryed, and well approved to be ſound in the faith, and skilfull to convince gain-ſayers and ſeducers; The more you help truth, and the ſervants of truth, the more help doe you therein contribute againſt errours, and the enemies of truth: No bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter help againſt darkneſſe, then light.</p>
               <p n="7">7. By <hi>a tender and watchfull eye unto the Vniverſities,</hi> one of which is lately fallen into your poſſeſſion: take care it may not fall into the poſſeſſion of any ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: you have heard (I doubt not) of a late Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Oxford;</hi> where ſome body undertook to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain (beſides in private) divers ſtrange and dangerous opinions in publique; I humbly intreat you to take care, that the Serpent gets not in his body, before there be any planted to bruiſe his head: Truth by right is the firſt-born, and ſhould firſt inherit: doe not put the truth to play an after game with errour; Other Garriſons, if loſt, may eaſily be reduced: but that which is ſurprized faſt by errour, is not ſo eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
               <p n="8">8. By <hi>injoyning a ſolemn day of Humiliation through all the Land, for the diſhonours redounding to God, and Chriſt, and the Truth, by the preſent errors, hereſies, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies;</hi> You did ſo lately for the flouds of rain which endangered the Com: O that it might ſeem good unto you ſo to doe, for the floud of errours which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger ſouls! This humble requeſt I preſume to leave with your pious zeal and prudence.</p>
               <p n="9">9. By <hi>uſing you Coercive power with ſuch methods and propertions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the reall ſafety of truth and ſouls doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and the repreſsion of dangerous errors doth need:</hi> So managing the diſtributions thereof, that under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of reſtraining hereſie, you by no means injure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113986:23"/>
ſanctity, nor yet under the pretence of ſanctity, you doe not favour the growth of hereſie: O what an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py people are they, amongſt whom errours are lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and truths are graining! where piety thrives, and wickedneſſe blaſts! where all who are good can joyn againſt all that is evill, and in leſſer things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as yet they cannot (through weakneſſe) claſp opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yet (for the truth and peace's ſake) can claſp hearts and hands to promote Gods glory, and the common ſalvation of ſouls!</p>
               <p n="2">2. I have a word alſo to ſay unto you who are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt: Come you forth from your long ſilences, neglects, and reſerves: and help the Church of Chriſt, in ſwallowing up the floud which the Serpent hath caſt out of his mouth: when Jeſus Chriſt is blaſphemed, it is not a time to fear, but to cry out, ſo ſpake <hi>Luther</hi> to <hi>Staupitius;</hi> Men will ſay that you are moderate and diſcreet, but what will Chriſt ſay to you, if at ſuch a time you be ſilent in his Cauſe? O my brethren! you are the husbandmen, take heed that none ſow tares in the field, whiles you ſleep: you are the builders, O bee ſure to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the foundation ſafe: you are the Shepherds of the Flock, O beware of the Wolves, leſt they break in and deſtroy the ſheep! You are the Vine-dreſſers, and keepers of the Vineyard, O have an eye to the Foxes, which elſe will ſpoil the tender Grapes! You are the Stewards of Chriſt, O be vigilant on what proviſion the houſhold doth feed! You are the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, O look out, leſt the enemy ſlip in and ſurpriſe the City! You are the Fathers, bee ſure that your children have not a ſtone given to them in ſtead of bread, or a Serpent in ſtead of a Fiſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113986:23"/>
You muſt help with your moſt fervent prayers: as <hi>Alexander</hi> once did, and prevailed againſt <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi> You muſt help with your counſels, with your watchings, with your preachings; You muſt <hi>bona do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp; mala dedocere,</hi> as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaks; You muſt be <hi>defenſores,</hi> and <hi>debellatores,</hi> ſtand for truth, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand errours: You are (in a ſingular manner) intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with truth and ſouls. O watch, O pray, O preach, O doe all that faithfull Miniſters ſhould doe, when a floud breaks in: You read of <hi>Eliahs</hi> zeal againſt the falſe Prophets, and of <hi>Pauls</hi> zeal againſt falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: You have read of the zeal of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> againſt the <hi>Arians:</hi> and of the zeal of <hi>Cyprian</hi> againſt the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatians:</hi> and of the zeal of <hi>Auſtine</hi> againſt the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> againſt the <hi>Manichees,</hi> againſt the <hi>Pelagians:</hi> You have read of the zeal of <hi>Hierome,</hi> of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> and many others in ancient times: You have read of the zeal of <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and others in later times: You have ſhewed your zeal to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in our dangerous times; I ſay no more, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your firſt works, remember your engagements, and be zealous: If you who are the Angels of Chriſt, the Miniſters of Chriſt, the Stewards of Chriſt, if you be drowzie, if you be ſilent, if you ſtop your own mouths, when mouths are opened againſt your Chriſt, whoſe mouth can we expect ſhould open it ſelf to ſwallow up the floud? It was a brave anſwer which <hi>Cyrill</hi> gave to <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> that in our private and perſonall injuries we ſhould hold our peace: but when the truth (or faith) is endangered to be corrupted, we ought to ſpeak, elſe we muſt give an account to God of our unſeaſonable ſilence.</p>
               <p>I have but one uſe more: Hath the Serpent caſt out
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113986:24"/>
ſuch a floud of errours and falſe doctrines amongſt us, then</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let every one take heed, leſt he be caried away with any part of this floud: I ſay, take heed: For erroneous times, are trying times, and proving times, as well as bloudy and perſecuting times: God hath tryed your fidelity to this Kingdome (of late) by a floud of bloud: and God is now trying your fidelity to the Kingdom of his dear Son, by a floud of errours; Take heed leſt you be carried away by this floud: There are ſeven things which are very apt to bee carried away by a floud; 1. Light things. 2. Looſe things. 3. Weak things. 4. Low things. 5. Rotten things. 6. Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering things. 7. Venturous things. O take heed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That you be not <hi>light</hi> or <hi>proud</hi> Chriſtians: er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours are moſt apt to breed in a proud brain and a graceleſſe heart: and no man is more likely to bee overturned by errour, then he who hath overturned himſelf by pride; the proud and blaſphemers are joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. The proud man is expoſed to moſt temptations, to moſt fals, and to moſt errors: 'Tis the proud man who conſents not to wholeſome words of Chriſt, but <hi>dotes about queſtions,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 3, 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That you be not <hi>looſe</hi> Chriſtians: If ungodlines be in the heart, it will not be hard for errour to get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the head: A looſe heart can beſt comply with looſe principles: Truth is ſearching and reforming, but er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is more quiet and gratifying: 'tis grace which ſettles the minde, and ſtabliſheth the heart.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That you be not <hi>weak</hi> Chriſtians: weake ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs are moſt longing: A Chriſtian whoſe faith is implicit, and leaning on man, doth often truſt out his judgement and ſoul: The weaker light you have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113986:24"/>
of truth, the more eaſily may you be cheated with errours in ſtead of truth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That you bee not <hi>low</hi> Chriſtians: a worldly heart is a very low heart: It is of all other the chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, it will be bought and ſold upon every turn to ſerve its own turn: The truth can never be ſure in that cheſt, which any errour with a little golden key can pick. If thou be the ſervant of truth for gain, thou wilt be a ſlave to errour for more gain.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That you be not <hi>rotten</hi> or <hi>hypocriticall</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: they were given up <hi>to beleeve lies who did not receive the truth in the love of it:</hi> How juſt is it with God, that he ſhould fall into reall errour, whoſe heart did never love reall truth? that the deceitfull heart ſhould at length be a deceived heart? Is it difficult to ſet him againſt the faith, who never had a ſound faith?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Take heed that you be not <hi>tottering</hi> and <hi>unſtable</hi> Chriſtians: when the judgement is not ballanced and ſolidly fixed upon the truths of Chriſt, but reeling and wavering, and like them in <hi>Eliahs</hi> time, halting between two opinions; it is uſually in danger to bee poiſed with errour: He whoſe mind is but indifferent about a truth, is more then half on his way to errour.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That you be not <hi>venturous</hi> and <hi>ſoul-tempting</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: <hi>Julian</hi> ſipt in his Apoſtaſie by going to hear <hi>Libanius:</hi> The Devill is ready enough to tempt you, be not you found to tempt him: <hi>Eve</hi> loſt all by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one Sermon from the mouth of the <hi>Serpent:</hi> If you will be trading amongſt cheaters, it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if you be cheated: we are ſure to goe by the worſt, when we venture upon our own ſtrength: the man who will expoſe himſelf to hear new truths, doth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113986:25"/>
oft times come back with old errours newly dreſſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let every one ſtrengthen his ſoul, that he may ſtand and withſtand, and not be carried away, &amp;c. The houſe built upon the Rock ſtood when the floud came: Take all in a word; a judgement ſolidly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled: an heart ſincerely renued: a faith truly bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed: Truth and love of it cordially matched: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and practiſe well joyned: a fear of our ſelves and dependance on God ſtill maintained: Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and the ſociety of humble and growing Chriſtians ſtill frequented: watchfulneſſe and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtill continued, are the beſt directives (that I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver) to keep us in the truth, and the beſt preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives (that I doe know) to keep us from errours.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
